<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--SinusitisGL_Text.rtf-->
<!DOCTYPE guideline.document SYSTEM "GEM_DTD.dtd">
<guideline.document>
	<guideline.header>
		<identity source="nd">
			<title source="nd">Clinical Practice Guideline: Management of Sinusitis</title>
			<citation source="explicit">Subcommittee on Management of Sinusitis and Committee on Quality Improvement 108 (3): 798       PEDIATRICS Vol. 108 No. 3 September 2001, pp. 798-808 AMERICAN ACADEMY OF PEDIATRICS: Clinical Practice Guideline: Management of Sinusitis Subcommittee on Management of Sinusitis and Committee on Quality Improvement<guideline.length source="nd"/>
			</citation>
			<release.date source="explicit">September 2001</release.date>
			<availability source="nd">
				<electronic source="nd"/>
				<print source="nd"/>
				<contact source="nd"/>
			</availability>
			<status source="nd"/>
			<companion.document source="nd">
				<patient.resource source="nd"/>
			</companion.document>
			<adaptation source="nd"/>
		</identity>
		<developer source="nd">
			<developer.name source="explicit">AMERICAN ACADEMY OF PEDIATRICS<developer.type>Medical Speciality Society</developer.type>
			</developer.name>
			<committee.name source="explicit">Subcommittee on Management of Sinusitis and Committee on Quality Improvement<committee.expertise source="explicit">A subcommittee, composed of pediatricians with expertise in infectious disease, allergy, epidemiology, family practice, and pediatric practice, supplemented with an otolaryngologist and radiologist, were selected to formulate the practice parameter.</committee.expertise>
				<committee.member source="explicit">Ellen R. Wald, MD<member.expertise source="explicit">Chairperson</member.expertise>
				</committee.member>
				<committee.member source="explicit">W. Clayton Bordley, MD, MPH<member.expertise source="nd"/></committee.member><committee.member source="explicit">David H. Darrow, MD, DDS<member.expertise source="nd"/></committee.member><committee.member source="explicit">Katherine Teets Grimm, MD<member.expertise source="nd"/></committee.member><committee.member source="explicit">Jack M. Gwaltney, Jr, MD<member.expertise source="nd"/></committee.member><committee.member source="explicit">S. Michael Marcy, MD<member.expertise source="nd"/></committee.member><committee.member source="explicit">Melvin O. Senac, Jr, MD<member.expertise source="nd"/></committee.member><committee.member source="explicit">Paul V. Williams, MD<member.expertise source="nd"/></committee.member><committee.member source="explicit">Larry Culpepper, MD, MPH<member.expertise source="explicit">American Academy of Family Physicians</member.expertise></committee.member><committee.member source="explicit">David L. Walner, MD<member.expertise source="explicit">American Academy of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery</member.expertise></committee.member><committee.member source="explicit">Carla Herrerias, MPH<member.expertise source="nd"/></committee.member><committee.member source="nd">Charles J. Homer, MD, MPH, Chairperson Richard D. Baltz, MD Michael J. Goldberg, MD Gerald B. Hickson, MD Paul V. Miles, MD Thomas B. Newman, MD, MPH Joan E. Shook, MD William M. Zurhellen, MD<member.expertise source="explicit">Committee on Quality Improvement,</member.expertise></committee.member><committee.member source="explicit">Charles H. Deitschel, Jr, MD Committee on Medical Liability Denise Dougherty, PhD Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality Institutions F. Lane France, MD Committee on Practice and Ambulatory Medicine Kelly J. Kelleher, MD, MPH Section on Epidemiology Betty A. Lowe, MD National Association of Children's Hospitals and Related Institutions Ellen Schwalenstocker, MBA National Association of Children's Hospitals and Related Institutions Richard N. Shiffman, MD Section on Computers and Other Technology<member.expertise source="explicit">Liaisons</member.expertise></committee.member></committee.name>
			<funding source="nd"/>
			<endorser source="nd"/>
			<comparable.guideline source="nd"/>
		</developer>
	</guideline.header>
	<guideline.body>
		<purpose source="nd">
			<main.focus source="explicit">diagnosis, evaluation, and treatment of children, ages 1 to 21 years, with uncomplicated acute, subacute, and recurrent acute bacterial sinusitis</main.focus>
			<category>Management</category>
			<rationale source="nd"/>
			<objective source="explicit">to encourage accurate diagnosis of bacterial sinusitis</objective>
			<objective source="explicit">appropriate use of imaging procedures</objective><objective source="explicit">judicious use of antibiotics</objective><objective source="explicit">The objective of treatment of acute bacterial sinusitis is to foster rapid recovery, prevent suppurative complications, and minimize exacerbations of asthma (reactive airways diseases).</objective><available.option source="nd"/>
			<implementation.strategy source="nd"/>
			<health.outcome source="nd"/>
			<exception source="nd"/>
		</purpose>
		<intended.audience source="nd">
			<users source="explicit">clinicians who treat children and adolescents<clinical.specialty/>
				<professional.group/>
			</users>
			<care.setting source="explicit">a variety of clinical settings including the office and emergency department.</care.setting>
		</intended.audience>
		<development.method source="nd">
			<description.evidence.collection source="explicit">The literature was searched in Medline, complemented by Excerpta Medica, from 1966 through March 1999, using the word "sinusitis." Search criteria were limited to human studies and English language and appropriate pediatric terms.<method.evidence.collection>Searches of Electronic Databases</method.evidence.collection>
				<number.source.documents source="explicit">More than 1800 citations were reviewed. One hundred thirty-eight articles were fully examined, resulting in 21 qualifying studies. These studies included 5 controlled randomized trials and 8 case series on antimicrobial therapy, 3 controlled randomized trials on ancillary treatments, and 8 studies with information on diagnostic tests.</number.source.documents>
			</description.evidence.collection>
			<evidence.time.period source="nd"/>
			<method.evidence.grading>Weighting According to a Scheme(Scheme Given)<rating.scheme source="explicit">Where data are lacking, a combination of evidence and expert opinion was used. Strong recommendations were based on high-quality scientific evidence or, when such was unavailable, strong expert consensus. Fair and weak recommendations are based on lesser-quality or limited data and expert consensus. Clinical options are identified as interventions for which the subcommittee could not find compelling positive or negative evidence. These clinical options are interventions that a reasonable health care professional may or may not wish to consider.</rating.scheme>
			</method.evidence.grading>
			<description.evidence.combination source="explicit">The heterogeneity and paucity of the data did not allow for formal meta-analysis. When possible, rates were pooled across different studies and heterogeneity assessed.<method.evidence.combination>Systematic Review</method.evidence.combination>
			</description.evidence.combination>
			<cost.analysis source="nd"/>
			<specification.harm.benefit source="nd"/>
			<quantification.harm.benefit source="nd"/>
			<role.value.judgment source="nd"/>
			<role.patient.preference source="nd"/>
			<qualifying.statement source="explicit">This clinical practice guideline is not intended as a sole source of guidance in the diagnosis and management of acute bacterial sinusitis in children. It is designed to assist pediatricians by providing an analytic framework for evaluation and treatment. It is not intended to replace clinical judgment or establish a protocol for all patients with this condition.</qualifying.statement>
		</development.method>
		<target.population source="nd">
			<eligibility source="inferred">Test text<inclusion.criterion source="explicit">ages 1 to 21 years</inclusion.criterion>
				<inclusion.criterion source="explicit">uncomplicated acute, subacute, and recurrent acute bacterial sinusitis</inclusion.criterion><exclusion.criterion source="explicit">Neonates and children younger than 1 year</exclusion.criterion>
				<exclusion.criterion source="nd">children with previously recognized anatomic abnormalities of their paranasal sinuses (facial dysmorphisms or trauma), immunodeficiencies, cystic fibrosis, or immotile cilia syndrome</exclusion.criterion><exclusion.criterion source="explicit">The child who seems toxic should be hospitalized and is not considered in this algorithm.</exclusion.criterion></eligibility>
			<age/>
			<sex/>
		</target.population>
		<knowledge.components source="nd">
			<recommendation source="explicit">Recommendation 1<conditional source="nd">it is the concurrent presentation with high fever and purulent nasal discharge for at least 3 to 4 consecutive days that helps to define the severe presentation of acute bacterial sinusitis. Children with severe onset of acute bacterial sinusitis may have an intense headache that is above or behind the eye; in general, they seem to be moderately ill.<decision.variable source="explicit" decision.variable.id="dv1">high fever<value source="nd"/>
						<decision.variable.description source="nd"/>
						<test.parameter source="nd">
							<sensitivity source="nd"/>
							<specificity source="nd"/>
							<predictive.value source="nd"/>
						</test.parameter>
						<decision.variable.cost source="nd"/>
					</decision.variable>
					<decision.variable source="explicit" decision.variable.id="dv2">nasal discharge<value source="explicit">purulent</value><decision.variable.description source="nd"/><test.parameter source="nd"><sensitivity source="nd"/><specificity source="nd"/><predictive.value source="nd"/></test.parameter><decision.variable.cost source="nd"/></decision.variable><decision.variable source="nd" decision.variable.id="dv3">{duration}<value source="nd">at least 3 to 4 consecutive days</value><decision.variable.description source="nd"/><test.parameter source="nd"><sensitivity source="nd"/><specificity source="nd"/><predictive.value source="nd"/></test.parameter><decision.variable.cost source="nd"/></decision.variable><decision.variable source="nd" decision.variable.id="dv4">intense headache (that is above or behind the eye)<value source="explicit"/><decision.variable.description source="nd"/><test.parameter source="nd"><sensitivity source="nd"/><specificity source="nd"/><predictive.value source="nd"/></test.parameter><decision.variable.cost source="nd"/></decision.variable><decision.variable source="explicit" decision.variable.id="dv5">in general, they seem to be moderately ill.<value source="explicit"/><decision.variable.description source="nd"/><test.parameter source="nd"><sensitivity source="nd"/><specificity source="nd"/><predictive.value source="nd"/></test.parameter><decision.variable.cost source="nd"/></decision.variable><action source="nd" action.id="a1">{conclude} the severe presentation of acute bacterial sinusitis<action.benefit source="nd"/>
						<action.risk.harm source="nd"/>
						<action.description source="nd"/>
						<action.cost source="nd"/>
					</action>
					<reason source="nd"/>
					<evidence.quality source="nd"/>
					<recommendation.strength source="nd"/>
					<flexibility source="nd"/>
					<logic source="nd"/>
					<cost source="nd"/>
					<linkage source="nd"/>
					<reference source="nd"/>
					<certainty source="nd"/>
				</conditional>
				<imperative source="explicit">The diagnosis of acute bacterial sinusitis is based on clinical criteria in children who present with upper respiratory symptoms that are either persistent or severe<directive source="nd">
						<directive.benefit source="nd"/>
						<directive.risk.harm source="nd"/>
						<directive.description source="nd"/>
						<directive.cost source="nd"/>
					</directive>
					<reason source="nd"/>
					<evidence.quality source="nd"/>
					<recommendation.strength source="explicit">strong recommendation based on limited scientific evidence and strong consensus of the panel</recommendation.strength>
					<flexibility source="nd"/>
					<logic source="nd"/>
					<cost source="nd"/>
					<linkage source="nd"/>
					<reference source="nd"/>
					<certainty source="nd"/>
				</imperative>
			</recommendation>
			<recommendation source="explicit">Recommendation 2a<conditional source="nd">Imaging studies are not necessary to confirm a diagnosis of clinical sinusitis in children less than or equal to 6 years of age (<decision.variable source="inferred" decision.variable.id="dv6">age<value source="nd">less than or equal to 6 {years}</value><decision.variable.description source="nd"/><test.parameter source="nd"><sensitivity source="nd"/><specificity source="nd"/><predictive.value source="nd"/></test.parameter><decision.variable.cost source="nd"/></decision.variable><action source="explicit" action.id="a2">Imaging studies are not necessary to confirm a diagnosis of clinical sinusitis<action.benefit source="nd"/><action.risk.harm source="nd"/><action.description source="nd"/><action.cost source="nd"/></action><reason source="explicit">In children with persistent symptoms, the history of protracted respiratory symptoms (&gt;10 but &lt;30 days without evidence of improvement) predicted significantly abnormal radiographs (complete opacification, mucosal thickening of at least 4 mm, or an air-fluid level) in 80% of children.31 For children 6 years of age or younger, the history predicted abnormal sinus radiographs in 88% of children. Accordingly, in this age group, because a positive history predicts the finding of abnormal sinus radiographs so frequently (and because history plus abnormal radiographs results in a positive sinus aspirate in 75% of cases), radiographs can be safely omitted and a diagnosis of acute bacterial sinusitis can be made on clinical criteria alone.</reason><evidence.quality source="explicit">limited scientific evidence</evidence.quality><recommendation.strength source="explicit">strong recommendation based on limited scientific evidence and strong consensus of the panel</recommendation.strength><flexibility source="nd"/><logic source="nd"/><cost source="nd"/><linkage source="nd"/><reference source="explicit">31</reference><certainty source="nd"/></conditional><conditional source="explicit">In contrast to the general agreement that radiographs are not necessary in children 6 years of age or younger with persistent symptoms, the need for radiographs as a confirmatory test of acute sinusitis in children older than 6 years with persistent symptoms and for all children (regardless of age) with severe symptoms is controversial.<decision.variable source="inferred" decision.variable.id="dv7">age<value source="explicit">older than 6 years</value><decision.variable.description source="nd"/><test.parameter source="nd"><sensitivity source="nd"/><specificity source="nd"/><predictive.value source="nd"/></test.parameter><decision.variable.cost source="nd"/></decision.variable><decision.variable source="explicit" decision.variable.id="dv8">persistent symptoms<value source="explicit"/><decision.variable.description source="nd"/><test.parameter source="nd"><sensitivity source="nd"/><specificity source="nd"/><predictive.value source="nd"/></test.parameter><decision.variable.cost source="nd"/></decision.variable><decision.variable source="explicit" decision.variable.id="dv9">severe symptoms<value source="explicit"/><decision.variable.description source="nd"/><test.parameter source="nd"><sensitivity source="nd"/><specificity source="nd"/><predictive.value source="nd"/></test.parameter><decision.variable.cost source="nd"/></decision.variable><action source="nd" action.id="a3">the need for radiographs as a confirmatory test of acute sinusitis  is controversial.<action.benefit source="nd"/><action.risk.harm source="nd"/><action.description source="nd"/><action.cost source="nd"/></action><reason source="explicit">A normal radiograph is powerful evidence that bacterial sinusitis is not the cause of the clinical syndrome.34 However, the American College of Radiology has taken the position that the diagnosis of acute uncomplicated sinusitis should be made on clinical grounds alone.35 They support this position by noting that plain radiographs of the paranasal sinuses are technically difficult to perform, particularly in very young children. Correct positioning may be difficult to achieve and therefore the radiographic images may overestimate and underestimate the presence of abnormalities within the paranasal sinuses.36,37 The college would reserve the use of images for situations in which the patient does not recover or worsens during the course of appropriate antimicrobial therapy. Similarly, a recent set of guidelines generated by the Sinus and Allergy Health Partnership (representing numerous constituencies) does not recommend either radiographs or computed tomography (CT) or magnetic resonance imaging scans to diagnose uncomplicated cases of acute bacterial sinusitis in any age group.1</reason><reason source="explicit">t is essential to recognize that abnormal images of the sinuses (either radiographs, CT, or magnetic resonance imaging) cannot stand alone as diagnostic evidence of acute bacterial sinusitis under any circumstances. Images can serve only as confirmatory measures of sinus disease in patients whose clinical histories are supportive of the diagnosis.</reason><evidence.quality source="explicit"/><recommendation.strength source="explicit"/><flexibility source="nd"/><logic source="nd">IF( dv7 &lt; 6 yrs and dv8) OR DV9 THEN  a3</logic><cost source="nd"/><linkage source="nd"/><reference source="nd">35, 36,37</reference><certainty source="nd"/></conditional><imperative source="nd"><directive source="nd"><directive.benefit source="nd"/><directive.risk.harm source="nd"/><directive.description source="nd"/><directive.cost source="nd"/></directive><reason source="nd"/><evidence.quality source="nd"/><recommendation.strength source="explicit"/><flexibility source="nd"/><logic source="nd"/><cost source="nd"/><linkage source="nd"/><reference source="nd"/><certainty source="nd"/></imperative></recommendation><recommendation source="explicit">Recommendation 2b<conditional source="explicit">CT scans of the paranasal sinuses should be reserved for patients in whom surgery is being considered as a management strategy<decision.variable source="explicit" decision.variable.id="dv10">patients in whom surgery is being considered as a management strategy<value source="nd"/><decision.variable.description source="nd"/><test.parameter source="nd"><sensitivity source="nd"/><specificity source="nd"/><predictive.value source="nd"/></test.parameter><decision.variable.cost source="nd"/></decision.variable><action source="explicit" action.id="a4">CT scans of the paranasal sinuses should be reserved<action.benefit source="nd"/><action.risk.harm source="nd"/><action.description source="nd"/><action.cost source="nd"/></action><reason source="explicit">Despite the limitations of CT scans,338-40 they offer a detailed image of sinus anatomy and, when taken in conjunction with clinical findings, remain a useful adjunct to guide surgical treatment.</reason><evidence.quality source="explicit">good evidence</evidence.quality><recommendation.strength source="explicit">strong recommendation based on good evidence and strong panel consensus)</recommendation.strength><flexibility source="nd"/><logic source="nd"/><cost source="nd"/><linkage source="nd"/><reference source="explicit">33</reference><certainty source="nd"/></conditional><imperative source="nd"><directive source="nd"><directive.benefit source="nd"/><directive.risk.harm source="nd"/><directive.description source="nd"/><directive.cost source="nd"/></directive><reason source="nd"/><evidence.quality source="nd"/><recommendation.strength source="explicit"/><flexibility source="nd"/><logic source="nd"/><cost source="nd"/><linkage source="nd"/><reference source="nd"/><certainty source="nd"/></imperative></recommendation><recommendation source="explicit">Recommendation 3<conditional source="explicit">Most patients with acute bacterial sinusitis who are treated with an appropriate antimicrobial agent respond promptly (within 48-72 hours) with a diminution of respiratory symptoms (reduction of nasal discharge and cough) and an improvement in general well-being.11,23,31 If a patient fails to improve, either the antimicrobial is ineffective or the diagnosis of sinusitis is not correct.<decision.variable source="explicit" decision.variable.id="dv11">diminution of respiratory symptoms (reduction of nasal discharge and cough)<value source="nd"/><decision.variable.description source="nd"/><test.parameter source="nd"><sensitivity source="nd"/><specificity source="nd"/><predictive.value source="nd"/></test.parameter><decision.variable.cost source="nd"/></decision.variable><decision.variable source="explicit" decision.variable.id="dv12">an improvement in general well-being.<value source="nd"/><decision.variable.description source="nd"/><test.parameter source="nd"><sensitivity source="nd"/><specificity source="nd"/><predictive.value source="nd"/></test.parameter><decision.variable.cost source="nd"/></decision.variable><decision.variable source="explicit" decision.variable.id="dv13">within 48-72 hours)<value source="nd"/><decision.variable.description source="nd"/><test.parameter source="nd"><sensitivity source="nd"/><specificity source="nd"/><predictive.value source="nd"/></test.parameter><decision.variable.cost source="nd"/></decision.variable><action source="explicit" action.id="a5">either the antimicrobial is ineffective or the diagnosis of sinusitis is not correct.<action.benefit source="nd"/><action.risk.harm source="nd"/><action.description source="nd"/><action.cost source="nd"/></action><reason source="explicit"/><evidence.quality source="explicit"/><recommendation.strength source="explicit"/><flexibility source="nd"/><logic source="nd"/><cost source="nd"/><linkage source="nd"/><reference source="explicit"/><certainty source="nd"/></conditional><conditional source="explicit">If patients do not improve while receiving the usual dose of amoxicillin (45 mg/kg/d), have recently been treated with an antimicrobial, have an illness that is moderate or more severe, or attend day care, therapy should be initiated with high-dose amoxicillin-clavulanate (80-90 mg/kg/d of amoxicillin component, with 6.4 mg/kg/d of clavulanate in 2 divided doses).<decision.variable source="explicit" decision.variable.id="dv14">do not improve while receiving the usual dose of amoxicillin (45 mg/kg/d),<value source="nd"/><decision.variable.description source="nd"/><test.parameter source="nd"><sensitivity source="nd"/><specificity source="nd"/><predictive.value source="nd"/></test.parameter><decision.variable.cost source="nd"/></decision.variable><decision.variable source="explicit" decision.variable.id="dv15">have recently been treated with an antimicrobial<value source="nd"/><decision.variable.description source="nd"/><test.parameter source="nd"><sensitivity source="nd"/><specificity source="nd"/><predictive.value source="nd"/></test.parameter><decision.variable.cost source="nd"/></decision.variable><decision.variable source="explicit" decision.variable.id="dv16">have an illness that is moderate or more severe<value source="nd"/><decision.variable.description source="nd"/><test.parameter source="nd"><sensitivity source="nd"/><specificity source="nd"/><predictive.value source="nd"/></test.parameter><decision.variable.cost source="nd"/></decision.variable><decision.variable source="explicit" decision.variable.id="dv17">attend day care,<value source="nd"/><decision.variable.description source="nd"/><test.parameter source="nd"><sensitivity source="nd"/><specificity source="nd"/><predictive.value source="nd"/></test.parameter><decision.variable.cost source="nd"/></decision.variable><action source="explicit" action.id="a6">therapy should be initiated with high-dose amoxicillin-clavulanate<action.benefit source="nd"/><action.risk.harm source="nd"/><action.description source="explicit">80-90 mg/kg/d of amoxicillin component, with 6.4 mg/kg/d of clavulanate in 2 divided doses)</action.description><action.cost source="nd"/></action><reason source="explicit">his dose of amoxicillin will yield sinus fluid levels that exceed the minimum inhibitory concentration of all S pneumoniae that are intermediate in resistance to penicillin and most, but not all, highly resistant S pneumoniae. There is sufficient potassium clavulanate to inhibit all -lactamase producing H influenzae and M catarrhalis. Alternative therapies include cefdinir, cefuroxime, or cefpodoxime. A single dose of ceftriaxone (at 50 mg/kg/d), given either intravenously or intramuscularly, can be used in children with vomiting that precludes administration of oral antibiotics. Twenty-four hours later, when the child is clinically improved, an oral antibiotic is substituted to complete the therapy. Although trimethoprim-sulfamethoxazole and erythromycin-sulfisoxazole have traditionally been useful in the past as first- and second-line therapy for patients with acute bacterial sinusitis, recent pneumococcal surveillance studies indicate that resistance to these 2 combination agents is substantial.51,52 Therefore, when patients fail to improve while receiving amoxicillin, neither trimethoprim-sulfamethoxazole nor erythromycin-sulfisoxazole are appropriate choices for antimicrobial therapy.</reason><evidence.quality source="explicit"/><recommendation.strength source="explicit"/><flexibility source="nd"/><logic source="nd"/><cost source="nd"/><linkage source="nd"/><reference source="explicit"/><certainty source="nd"/></conditional><conditional source="explicit">For patients who do not improve with a second course of antibiotics or who are acutely ill, there are 2 options. It is appropriate to consult an otolaryngologist for consideration of maxillary sinus aspiration to obtain a sample of sinus secretions for culture and sensitivity so that therapy can be adjusted precisely. Alternatively, the physician may prescribe intravenous cefotaxime or ceftriaxone (either in hospital or at home) and refer to an otolaryngologist only if the patient does not improve on intravenous antibiotics.<decision.variable source="explicit" decision.variable.id="dv18">patients who do not improve with a second course of antibiotics<value source="nd"/><decision.variable.description source="nd"/><test.parameter source="nd"><sensitivity source="nd"/><specificity source="nd"/><predictive.value source="nd"/></test.parameter><decision.variable.cost source="nd"/></decision.variable><decision.variable source="explicit" decision.variable.id="dv19">are acutely ill<value source="nd"/><decision.variable.description source="nd"/><test.parameter source="nd"><sensitivity source="nd"/><specificity source="nd"/><predictive.value source="nd"/></test.parameter><decision.variable.cost source="nd"/></decision.variable><action source="explicit" action.id="a7">It is appropriate to consult an otolaryngologist for consideration of maxillary sinus aspiration<action.benefit source="nd"/><action.risk.harm source="nd"/><action.description source="explicit"/><action.cost source="nd"/></action><action source="explicit" action.id="a8">the physician may prescribe intravenous cefotaxime or ceftriaxone (either in hospital or at home) and refer to an otolaryngologist only if the patient does not improve on intravenous antibiotics.<action.benefit source="nd"/><action.risk.harm source="nd"/><action.description source="explicit"/><action.cost source="nd"/></action><reason source="explicit">obtain a sample of sinus secretions for culture and sensitivity so that therapy can be adjusted precisely.</reason><reason source="explicit"/><evidence.quality source="explicit"/><recommendation.strength source="explicit"/><flexibility source="nd"/><logic source="nd"/><cost source="nd"/><linkage source="nd"/><reference source="explicit"/><certainty source="nd"/></conditional><imperative source="explicit">Antibiotics are recommended for the management of acute bacterial sinusitis to achieve a more rapid clinical cure<directive source="nd" directive.id="dir1">Antibiotics are recommended for the management of acute bacterial sinusitis <directive.benefit source="explicit">children receiving antimicrobial therapy recovered more quickly and more often than those receiving placebo</directive.benefit><directive.benefit source="explicit">The desire to continue to use amoxicillin as first-line therapy in patients suspected of having acute bacterial sinusitis relates to its general effectiveness, safety, and tolerability; low cost; and narrow spectrum.</directive.benefit><directive.risk.harm source="nd"/><directive.description source="explicit">antimicrobials in adequate doses with appropriate antibacterial spectra are highly effective in eradicating or substantially reducing bacteria in the sinus cavity, whereas those with inadequate spectrum or given in inadequate doses are not</directive.description><directive.description source="explicit">The microbiology of acute, subacute, and recurrent acute bacterial sinusitis has been outlined in several studies.20-22 The principal bacterial pathogens are Streptococcus pneumoniae, nontypeable Haemophilus influenzae, and Moraxella catarrhalis. S pneumoniae is recovered from approximately 30% of children with acute bacterial sinusitis, whereas H influenzae and M catarrhalis are each recovered from about 20%.23 In the remaining 30% of children, aspirates of the maxillary sinus are sterile. It is noteworthy that neither Streptococcus aureus nor respiratory anaerobes are likely to be recovered from children with acute bacterial sinusitis.22</directive.description><directive.description source="explicit">For children younger than 2 years of age with uncomplicated acute bacterial sinusitis that is mild to moderate in degree of severity, who do not attend day care, and have not recently been treated with an antimicrobial, amoxicillin is recommended at either a usual dose of 45 mg/kg/d in 2 divided doses or a high dose of 90 mg/kg/d in 2 divided doses (Fig 1). If the patient is allergic to amoxicillin, either cefdinir (14 mg/kg/d in 1 or 2 doses), cefuroxime (30 mg/kg/d in 2 divided doses), or cefpodoxime (10 mg/kg/d once daily) can be used (only if the allergic reaction was not a type 1 hypersensitivity reaction). In cases of serious allergic reactions, clarithromycin (15 mg/kg/d in 2 divided doses) or azithromycin (10 mg/kg/d on day 1, 5 mg/kg/d × 4 days as a single daily dose) can be used in an effort to select an antimicrobial of an entirely different class. The Food and Drug Administration has not approved azithromycin for use in patients with sinusitis. Alternative therapy in the penicillin-allergic patient who is known to be infected with a penicillin-resistant S pneumoniae is clindamycin at 30 to 40 mg/kg/d in 3 divided doses.</directive.description><directive.description source="explicit">The optimal duration of therapy for patients with acute bacterial sinusitis has not received systematic study. Often empiric recommendations are made for 10, 14, 21, or 28 days of therapy. An alternative suggestion has been made that antibiotic therapy be continued until the patient becomes free of symptoms and then for an additional 7 days.23 This strategy, which individualizes treatment  for each patient, results in a minimum course of 10 days and avoids prolonged courses of antibiotics in patients who are asymptomatic and thereby unlikely to be compliant.</directive.description><directive.cost source="nd"/></directive><reason source="nd">to promote the judicious use of antibiotics, it is essential that children diagnosed as having acute bacterial sinusitis meet the defining clinical presentations of "persistent" or "severe" disease as described previously.41 This will minimize the number of children with uncomplicated viral upper respiratory tract infections who are treated with antimicrobials.</reason><evidence.quality source="explicit">good evidence</evidence.quality><recommendation.strength source="explicit">strong recommendation based on good evidence and strong panel consensus)</recommendation.strength><flexibility source="explicit">Risk factors for the presence of bacterial species that are likely to be resistant to amoxicillin include 1) attendance at day care, 2) recent receipt (&lt;90 days) of antimicrobial treatment, and 3) age less than 2 years.49,50</flexibility><logic source="nd"/><cost source="nd"/><linkage source="nd"/><reference source="nd"/><certainty source="nd"/></imperative></recommendation><recommendation source="explicit">Adjuvant Therapies No recommendations are made based on controversial and limited data.<conditional source="explicit"><decision.variable source="explicit"><value source="nd"/><decision.variable.description source="nd"/><test.parameter source="nd"><sensitivity source="nd"/><specificity source="nd"/><predictive.value source="nd"/></test.parameter><decision.variable.cost source="nd"/></decision.variable><action source="explicit"><action.benefit source="nd"/><action.risk.harm source="nd"/><action.description source="nd"/><action.cost source="nd"/></action><reason source="explicit"/><evidence.quality source="explicit"/><recommendation.strength source="explicit"/><flexibility source="nd"/><logic source="nd"/><cost source="nd"/><linkage source="nd"/><reference source="explicit"/><certainty source="nd"/></conditional><imperative source="explicit"><directive source="nd"><directive.benefit source="explicit"/><directive.benefit source="explicit"/><directive.risk.harm source="nd"/><directive.description source="explicit"/><directive.description source="explicit"/><directive.description source="explicit"/><directive.description source="explicit"/><directive.cost source="nd"/></directive><reason source="nd"/><evidence.quality source="explicit"/><recommendation.strength source="explicit"/><flexibility source="explicit"/><logic source="nd"/><cost source="nd"/><linkage source="nd"/><reference source="nd"/><certainty source="nd"/></imperative></recommendation><recommendation source="explicit">Antibiotic Prophylaxis No recommendations are made based on limited and controversial data.<conditional source="explicit"><decision.variable source="explicit"><value source="nd"/><decision.variable.description source="nd"/><test.parameter source="nd"><sensitivity source="nd"/><specificity source="nd"/><predictive.value source="nd"/></test.parameter><decision.variable.cost source="nd"/></decision.variable><action source="explicit"><action.benefit source="nd"/><action.risk.harm source="nd"/><action.description source="nd"/><action.cost source="nd"/></action><reason source="explicit"/><evidence.quality source="explicit"/><recommendation.strength source="explicit"/><flexibility source="nd"/><logic source="nd"/><cost source="nd"/><linkage source="nd"/><reference source="explicit"/><certainty source="nd"/></conditional><imperative source="explicit"><directive source="nd"><directive.benefit source="explicit"/><directive.benefit source="explicit"/><directive.risk.harm source="nd"/><directive.description source="explicit"/><directive.description source="explicit"/><directive.description source="explicit"/><directive.description source="explicit"/><directive.cost source="nd"/></directive><reason source="nd"/><evidence.quality source="explicit"/><recommendation.strength source="explicit"/><flexibility source="explicit"/><logic source="nd"/><cost source="nd"/><linkage source="nd"/><reference source="nd"/><certainty source="nd"/></imperative></recommendation><recommendation source="explicit">Complementary/Alternative Medicine for Prevention and Treatment of Rhinosinusitis No recommendations are made based on limited and controversial data.<conditional source="explicit"><decision.variable source="explicit"><value source="nd"/><decision.variable.description source="nd"/><test.parameter source="nd"><sensitivity source="nd"/><specificity source="nd"/><predictive.value source="nd"/></test.parameter><decision.variable.cost source="nd"/></decision.variable><action source="explicit"><action.benefit source="nd"/><action.risk.harm source="nd"/><action.description source="nd"/><action.cost source="nd"/></action><reason source="explicit"/><evidence.quality source="explicit"/><recommendation.strength source="explicit"/><flexibility source="nd"/><logic source="nd"/><cost source="nd"/><linkage source="nd"/><reference source="explicit"/><certainty source="nd"/></conditional><imperative source="explicit"><directive source="nd"><directive.benefit source="explicit"/><directive.benefit source="explicit"/><directive.risk.harm source="nd"/><directive.description source="explicit"/><directive.description source="explicit"/><directive.description source="explicit"/><directive.description source="explicit"/><directive.cost source="nd"/></directive><reason source="nd"/><evidence.quality source="explicit"/><recommendation.strength source="explicit"/><flexibility source="explicit"/><logic source="nd"/><cost source="nd"/><linkage source="nd"/><reference source="nd"/><certainty source="nd"/></imperative></recommendation><recommendation source="explicit">4<conditional source="explicit">Children with complications or suspected complications of acute bacterial sinusitis should be treated promptly and aggressively. This should include referral to an otolaryngologist usually with the consultation of an infectious disease specialist, ophthalmologist, and neurosurgeon<decision.variable source="explicit" decision.variable.id="dv20">complications or suspected complications of acute bacterial sinusitis<value source="nd"/><decision.variable.description source="nd"/><test.parameter source="nd"><sensitivity source="nd"/><specificity source="nd"/><predictive.value source="nd"/></test.parameter><decision.variable.cost source="nd"/></decision.variable><action source="explicit" action.id="a9">be treated promptly and aggressively. This should include referral to an otolaryngologist usually with the consultation of an infectious disease specialist, ophthalmologist, and neurosurgeon<action.benefit source="nd"/><action.risk.harm source="nd"/><action.description source="nd"/><action.cost source="nd"/></action><reason source="nd"/><evidence.quality source="explicit"/><recommendation.strength source="explicit">strong recommendation based on strong consensus of the panel)</recommendation.strength><flexibility source="nd"/><logic source="nd"/><cost source="nd"/><linkage source="nd"/><reference source="explicit"/><certainty source="nd"/></conditional><conditional source="explicit">Mild cases of periorbital cellulitis (eyelid &lt;50% closed) may be treated with appropriate oral antibiotic therapy as an outpatient with daily patient encounters.<decision.variable source="explicit" decision.variable.id="dv21">Mild cases of periorbital cellulitis (eyelid &lt;50% closed)<value source="nd"/><decision.variable.description source="nd"/><test.parameter source="nd"><sensitivity source="nd"/><specificity source="nd"/><predictive.value source="nd"/></test.parameter><decision.variable.cost source="nd"/></decision.variable><action source="explicit" action.id="a10">may be treated with appropriate oral antibiotic therapy as an outpatient with daily patient encounters.<action.benefit source="nd"/><action.risk.harm source="nd"/><action.description source="nd"/><action.cost source="nd"/></action><reason source="nd"/><evidence.quality source="explicit"/><recommendation.strength source="explicit"/><flexibility source="nd"/><logic source="nd"/><cost source="nd"/><linkage source="nd"/><reference source="explicit"/><certainty source="nd"/></conditional><conditional source="nd">if the patient {with mild periorbital cellulitis} has not improved in 24 to 48 hours or if the infection is progressing rapidly, it is appropriate to admit the patient to the hospital for antimicrobial therapy consisting of intravenous ceftriaxone<decision.variable source="explicit" decision.variable.id="dv22">Mild cases of periorbital cellulitis (eyelid &lt;50% closed)<value source="nd"/><decision.variable.description source="nd"/><test.parameter source="nd"><sensitivity source="nd"/><specificity source="nd"/><predictive.value source="nd"/></test.parameter><decision.variable.cost source="nd"/></decision.variable><decision.variable source="nd" decision.variable.id="dv23">{clinical status}<value source="inferred">not improved in 24 to 48 hours or infection is progressing rapidly</value><decision.variable.description source="nd"/><test.parameter source="nd"><sensitivity source="nd"/><specificity source="nd"/><predictive.value source="nd"/></test.parameter><decision.variable.cost source="nd"/></decision.variable><action source="explicit" action.id="a11">admit the patient to the hospital for antimicrobial therapy consisting of intravenous ceftriaxone (100 mg/kg/d in 2 divided doses) or ampicillin-sulbactam (200 mg/kg/d in 4 divided doses). Vancomycin (60 mg/kg/d in 4 divided doses) may be added in children in whom infection is either known or likely to be caused by S pneumoniae that are highly resistant to penicillin.<action.benefit source="nd"/><action.risk.harm source="nd"/><action.description source="nd"/><action.cost source="nd"/></action><reason source="nd"/><evidence.quality source="explicit"/><recommendation.strength source="explicit"/><flexibility source="nd"/><logic source="nd"/><cost source="nd"/><linkage source="nd"/><reference source="explicit"/><certainty source="nd"/></conditional><conditional source="explicit">If proptosis, impaired visual acuity, or impaired extraocular mobility are present on examination, a CT scan (preferably coronal thin cut with contrast) of the orbits/sinuses is essential to exclude a suppurative complication. In such cases, the patient should be evaluated by an otolaryngologist and an ophthalmologist.<decision.variable source="explicit" decision.variable.id="dv25">proptosis<value source="nd"/><decision.variable.description source="nd"/><test.parameter source="nd"><sensitivity source="nd"/><specificity source="nd"/><predictive.value source="nd"/></test.parameter><decision.variable.cost source="nd"/></decision.variable><decision.variable source="explicit" decision.variable.id="dv26">impaired visual acuity<value source="nd"/><decision.variable.description source="nd"/><test.parameter source="nd"><sensitivity source="nd"/><specificity source="nd"/><predictive.value source="nd"/></test.parameter><decision.variable.cost source="nd"/></decision.variable><decision.variable source="explicit" decision.variable.id="dv27">impaired extraocular mobility<value source="nd"/><decision.variable.description source="nd"/><test.parameter source="nd"><sensitivity source="nd"/><specificity source="nd"/><predictive.value source="nd"/></test.parameter><decision.variable.cost source="nd"/></decision.variable><action source="explicit" action.id="a12">a CT scan (preferably coronal thin cut with contrast) of the orbits/sinuses is essential to exclude a suppurative complication.<action.benefit source="nd"/><action.risk.harm source="nd"/><action.description source="nd"/><action.cost source="nd"/></action><action source="explicit" action.id="a13">the patient should be evaluated by an otolaryngologist and an ophthalmologist.<action.benefit source="nd"/><action.risk.harm source="nd"/><action.description source="nd"/><action.cost source="nd"/></action><reason source="explicit">Suppurative complications generally require prompt surgical drainage.</reason><evidence.quality source="explicit"/><recommendation.strength source="explicit"/><flexibility source="nd"/><logic source="nd"/><cost source="nd"/><linkage source="nd"/><reference source="explicit"/><certainty source="nd"/></conditional><conditional source="explicit">In patients with altered mental status, neurosurgical consultation is indicated. Signs of increased intracranial pressure (headache and vomiting) or nuchal rigidity require immediate CT scanning (with contrast) of the brain, orbits, and sinuses to exclude intracranial complications such as cavernous sinus thrombosis, osteomyelitis of the frontal bone (Pott's puffy tumor), meningitis, subdural empyema, epidural abscess, and brain abscess.<decision.variable source="explicit" decision.variable.id="dv28">altered mental status<value source="nd"/><decision.variable.description source="nd"/><test.parameter source="nd"><sensitivity source="nd"/><specificity source="nd"/><predictive.value source="nd"/></test.parameter><decision.variable.cost source="nd"/></decision.variable><action source="explicit" action.id="a14">neurosurgical consultation is indicated<action.benefit source="nd"/><action.risk.harm source="nd"/><action.description source="nd"/><action.cost source="nd"/></action><reason source="nd"/><evidence.quality source="explicit"/><recommendation.strength source="explicit"/><flexibility source="nd"/><logic source="nd"/><cost source="nd"/><linkage source="nd"/><reference source="explicit"/><certainty source="nd"/></conditional><conditional source="explicit">Signs of increased intracranial pressure (headache and vomiting) or nuchal rigidity require immediate CT scanning (with contrast) of the brain, orbits, and sinuses to exclude intracranial complications such as cavernous sinus thrombosis, osteomyelitis of the frontal bone (Pott's puffy tumor), meningitis, subdural empyema, epidural abscess, and brain abscess. Central nervous system complications, such as meningitis and empyemas, should be treated either with intravenous cefotaxime or ceftriaxone and vancomycin pending the results of culture and susceptibility testing.<decision.variable source="explicit" decision.variable.id="dv29">Signs of increased intracranial pressure (headache and vomiting) or nuchal rigidity<value source="nd"/><decision.variable.description source="nd"/><test.parameter source="nd"><sensitivity source="nd"/><specificity source="nd"/><predictive.value source="nd"/></test.parameter><decision.variable.cost source="nd"/></decision.variable><action source="explicit" action.id="a15">immediate CT scanning (with contrast) of the brain, orbits, and sinuses<action.benefit source="nd"/><action.risk.harm source="nd"/><action.description source="nd"/><action.cost source="nd"/></action><reason source="explicit">to exclude intracranial complications such as cavernous sinus thrombosis, osteomyelitis of the frontal bone (Pott's puffy tumor), meningitis, subdural empyema, epidural abscess, and brain abscess.</reason><evidence.quality source="explicit"/><recommendation.strength source="explicit"/><flexibility source="nd"/><logic source="nd"/><cost source="nd"/><linkage source="nd"/><reference source="explicit"/><certainty source="nd"/></conditional><imperative source="explicit"><directive source="nd"><directive.benefit source="explicit"/><directive.benefit source="explicit"/><directive.risk.harm source="nd"/><directive.description source="explicit"/><directive.description source="explicit"/><directive.description source="explicit"/><directive.description source="explicit"/><directive.cost source="nd"/></directive><reason source="nd"/><evidence.quality source="explicit"/><recommendation.strength source="explicit"/><flexibility source="explicit"/><logic source="nd"/><cost source="nd"/><linkage source="nd"/><reference source="nd"/><certainty source="nd"/></imperative></recommendation><definition source="nd">
				<term source="inferred">acute bacterial sinusitis<term.meaning source="explicit">Bacterial infection of the paranasal sinuses lasting less than 30 days in which symptoms resolve completely.</term.meaning>
				</term>
				<term source="inferred">subacute bacterial sinusitis<term.meaning source="explicit">ymptoms resolve completely.</term.meaning></term><term source="inferred">recurrent acute bacterial sinusitis
<term.meaning source="explicit">Episodes of bacterial infection of the paranasal sinuses, each lasting less than 30 days and separated by intervals of at least 10 days during which the patient is asymptomatic.</term.meaning></term><term source="inferred">chronic sinusitis<term.meaning source="explicit">Episodes of inflammation of the paranasal sinuses lasting more than 90 days. Patients have persistent residual respiratory symptoms such as cough, rhinorrhea, or nasal obstruction.</term.meaning></term><term source="inferred">acute bacterial sinusitis superimposed on chronic sinusitis<term.meaning source="explicit">Patients with residual respiratory symptoms develop new respiratory symptoms. When treated with antimicrobials, these new symptoms resolve, but the underlying residual symptoms do not.</term.meaning></term><term source="explicit">Persistent symptoms<term.meaning source="explicit">those that last longer than 10 to 14, but less than 30, days. Such symptoms include nasal or postnasal discharge (of any quality), daytime cough (which may be worse at night), or both.</term.meaning></term><term source="explicit">Severe symptoms<term.meaning source="explicit">a temperature of at least 102°F (39oC) and purulent nasal discharge present concurrently for at least 3 to 4 consecutive days in a child who seems ill.</term.meaning></term></definition>
			<algorithm source="nd">
				<action.step source="nd"/>
				<conditional.step source="nd"/>
				<branch.step source="nd"/>
				<synchronization.step source="nd"/>
			</algorithm>
		</knowledge.components>
		<testing source="nd">
			<external.review source="explicit">The draft clinical practice guideline underwent extensive peer review by committees and sections within the American Academy of Pediatrics and by numerous outside organizations. Liaisons to the committee also distributed the draft within their organizations.<review.method>External Peer Review</review.method>
			</external.review>
			<external.review source="explicit"><review.method source="ngc"/></external.review><pilot.testing source="nd"/>
		</testing>
		<revision.plan source="nd">
			<expiration source="nd"/>
			<scheduled.review source="nd"/>
		</revision.plan>
	</guideline.body>
</guideline.document>
