<!--<!DOCTYPE paper SYSTEM "extremepaper.xml.dtd" >
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="extreme.html.xsl" ?>-->
<paper>
<front>
<title>The Resource Directory Description Language (RDDL): What goes at the end of a namespace URI?</title>
<author contact="1">
  	<fname>Jonathan</fname>
	<surname>Borden</surname>
  	<jobtitle>Assistant Professor</jobtitle>
  	<address>
		<affil>Tufts University School of Medicine</affil>
  		<subaffil>Department of Neurosurgery</subaffil>
		<aline>New England Medical Center #178</aline>
		<aline>750 Washington Street</aline>
		<city>Boston</city><state>MA</state>
		<postcode>02111</postcode>
		<phone>617-636-5859</phone>
		<fax>617-636-7587</fax>
		<email>jborden@mediaone.net</email>
		<web>http://www.openhealth.org</web>
	</address>
  <bio><para>Dr. Jonathan Borden is an editor of the RDDL specification. 
  	An Assistant Professor of Neurosurgery at Tufts Universitym he is the Director of the Boston Gamma Knife Center. 
	He is the Director of the Open Healthcare Group, and a co-chair of the ASTM E31.25 XML Healthcare DTD subcommittee.</para></bio>
</author>
<keywords>
	<keyword>namespace</keyword>
	<keyword>RDDL</keyword>
	<keyword>XLink</keyword>
	<keyword>XHTML</keyword>
	<keyword>ontology</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>
	<para>
		The <cit>W3C XML Namespace Recommendation</cit> was designed to partition XML elements and attributes into 
		partitions given a unique namespace name or identifier. The recommendation, which defines a namespace name
		as a URI, provides no guidance as to what a resolvable URI ought resolve to. 
	</para>
	<para>
The Resource Directory Description Language (RDDL) was created to answer the 
question of: what ought an XML Namespace URI reference? RDDL uses an XHTML format in 
which resource elements are embedded. Each resource element contains a simple 
XLink referencing the related resource. By integrating namespaces and schemas, a view of XML Namespaces as both
names and spaces is presented.
	</para>


</abstract>
</front>
<body>
  <section><title>Introduction</title>
        <para>
         The W3C <cit>XML Namespaces Recommendation</cit> defines a mechanism to
         distinguish XML element names by a URI. The W3C XML Namespaces
         Recommendation is fairly succinct, precise and contains Extended
         Backus Nauer form (ENBF) productions which describe the syntax behind XML
         Namespaces as it relates to XML 1.0. With such a precise description,
         one wonders why such controvery ensues?
      </para>
      <para>
         Much of the controversy results from the usage of Uniform Resource
         Identifiers (URIs) as namespace names and the XML Namespaces
         Recommendation thus inherits the controversies and confusion regarding
         URIs.
	The use of URIs as a mechanism of namespace partitioning has been controversial 
	and confusing for several reasons:
	<seqlist>
	<li><para>For the computer science community: XML namespaces differ from traditional namespaces as traditional namespaces conventionally refer to a <highlight style="ital">set</highlight> whereas XML namespaces more properly refer to an <highlight style="ital">unbounded partition</highlight></para></li>
	<li><para>For the web community: Use of URIs which can be resolved (i.e URLs) suggests that XML namespace identifiers 'point to something' yet no guidance is provided on what they ought reference.</para></li>
	</seqlist>
	</para>
<para>    RDDL is simple, solves both of these problems, and works with 
the current Web infrastructure.</para>
<para>The Resource Directory Description Language is an extension of <highlight style="ital">W3C XHTML Basic 1.0</highlight> with an added 
element named <highlight style="ital">resource</highlight>. This element serves 
as an XLink to the referenced resource, and contains a human-readable 
description of the resource and machine readable links which describe the 
purpose of the link and the nature of the resource being linked to. The nature 
of the resource being linked to is indicated by the <highlight style="ital">xlink:role</highlight> 
attribute and the purpose of the link is indicated by the 
<highlight style="ital">xlink:arcrole</highlight> attribute. </para>
<para>The rddl:resource element is defined as:</para>
<verbatim>&lt;!ELEMENT rddl:resource (#PCDATA | %Flow.mix;)*&gt;
&lt;!ATTLIST rddl:resource
  id            ID       #IMPLIED
  xml:lang      NMTOKEN  #IMPLIED
  xml:base      CDATA    #IMPLIED
  xmlns:rddl    CDATA    #FIXED   "http://www.rddl.org/"
  xlink:type    (simple) #FIXED   "simple"
  xlink:arcrole CDATA    #IMPLIED
  xlink:role    CDATA             "http://www.rddl.org/#resource"
  xlink:href    CDATA    #IMPLIED
  xlink:title   CDATA    #IMPLIED
  xlink:embed   CDATA    #FIXED   "none"
  xlink:actuate CDATA    #FIXED   "none"
  &gt;
</verbatim>
	<para>For the computer science community, a proper 
namespace is created from an XML namespace as the <highlight style="bold">set</highlight> of 
fragment identifier qualified URI references contained in the RDDL document 
describing the XML namespace.</para>
<para>For the web community, a namespace name references a document which is 
readable by humans in popular browsers as well as providing machine readable 
links to resources related to the namespace. For example an "XML browser" would 
be able to locate code or plugins needed for the display of namespace qualified 
elements such as embedded SVG, MathML or other formats.</para>
<para>The RDDL specification itself serves as a RDDL description of the RDDL 
namespace URI <cit>http://www.rddl.org/</cit> . RDDL is 
described a DTD, and various schemata including RELAX, TREX, Schematron and XML 
Schema. In this context RDDL serves as a case study for the development and 
comparision of these various schema languages.</para>
<para>RDDL is now found at the end of the namespace URI for schema languages such 
as Schematron, XML Schema, and Examplotron, and for namespaces such as RSS 1.0, 
and the Comminity XSLT Extension effort.</para>
<para>Natures and purposes of namespace related resources are defined to be URI 
references according to XLink. RDDL defines common natures and purposes. The implications of RDDL 
for the understanding of XML Namespaces are presented.</para>
  </section>
  <section><title>Namespaces as names</title>
        <para>
         A traditional namespace is simply a set of names. Because XML elements
         and attributes share the namespace, a DTD or schema may define
         distinct but identically named elements and attributes. One might say
         that an XML Namespace is not a traditional namespace for this reason.
         This issue is not controversial, XML having inherited this
         &quot;feature&quot; from SGML.
      </para>
      <para>
         The controversial feature of <i>XML Namespaces</i> is the use of URIs
         as namespace names. URIs are widely used to name things on the World
         Wide Web (WWW) yet what is named on the WWW has traditionally been a
         document. Using a URI as a namespace name has created some
         controversy, yet really URIs are a rather conventional hierarchical
         naming convention Use as namespace names is not known to create
         problems for software programs which need to distinguish XML element
         and attribute names. What has created controversy is the desire by
         many to understand in a more tangible fashion what a namespace is.
         This paper suggests that understanding a namespace as a <i>space</i>
         may provide some insight in this regard.
      </para>
	  </section>
	  <section><title>Namespaces as spaces</title>
      <p>
         A space such as <i>Cartesian</i> space may have a set number of
         dimensions and other defining characteristics. The behavior of objects
         within the space is defined by a set of rules e.g. <i>Newtonian
         Mechanics</i>.
      </p>
      <p>
         Other spaces may have a different number of dimensions and operate
         under a different set of rules such as <i>quatum mechanics</i> and
         <i>String Theory</i>.
      </p>
      <p>
         A <i>Data Space</i> is defined by an architecture. Such an
         architecture can be visualized by a graph of nodes connected by arcs.
         Such graphical representations can be generated from schemata.
      </p></section>
	  <section><title>The shape of information</title>
      <p>
         XML documents have often been described to have a <i>treelike</i>
         structure. More generally data structures can be described by graphs.
         Such data structures are easy to visualize. We can understand XML
         documents having a shallow arborization or a deep arborization. A
         document consisting of a root element whose content is a long string
         is the most shallow type of arborization. One might imagine a shape
         transformation which matches the string against a regular expression
         pattern which results in the string being transformed into a hierarchy
         of nodes and values. Figure 1 demonstrates a regular exression
         representing a DNA sequence which is transformed into a hierarchy
         using terms such as &quot;gene&quot; and &quot;snp&quot;. This
         vocabulary is in the domain of molecular biology. Such a pattern or
         transform represents genetic information at two levels of abstraction.
      </p>
	  </section>
	  <section>
      <title>Tree space and path identifiers</title>
      <p>
         Just as Cartesian space defines a point as having an <i>x</i>,
         <i>y</i> and <i>z</i> coordinate, a tree is described by nodes having
         parents and children. A path is used to locate a node on a tree by
         starting with the root and traversing child nodes until the desired
         node is identified.
      </p>
      <p>
         In XML the XPath Recommendation describes such a hierarchical
         identification mechanism which has become quite popular perhaps due to
         its natural fit with XML.
      </p>
	  </section>
	  <section><title>URI Space</title>
      <p>
         A popular misconception is that a URL directly references an HTML
         document. Rather an URI (a URL being a type of URI) <i>identifies</i>
         a <i>resource</i> and that <i>resource</i> may be rendered at some
         point in time as an HTML document. This concept of the abstract
         resource is understood as a point in URI space.
      </p>
      <p>
         URI Space is organized in a hierarchical fashion. At the root level,
         URIs are partitioned by <i>scheme</i> such as &quot;http&quot;,
         &quot;ftp&quot;, &quot;mid&quot; or &quot;urn&quot;. Individual
         schemes may be hierarchical or non hierarchical and the general syntax
         is defined in the famous RFC 2396. Many URI schemes use path syntaxes
         to identify resources.
      </p>
      <p>
         <img alt="error-file:TidyOut.log" src="Image1.gif" width="386"
         height="302" />
      </p>
	  </section>
	  <section>
	  <title>RDDL Space</title>
      <p>
         The <i>Resource Directory Description Language</i> (RDDL) is an
         attempt to define the format of a document suitable to be resolved (or
         rendered) as a result of dereferencing a namespace name URI. The RDDL
         format defines resources as simple Xlinks having a <i>nature</i> and
         <i>purpose</i>
      </p>
      <p>
         The <i>nature</i> of a RDDL resource is a URI which is the
         <i>xlink:role</i> of the simple XLink which describes the resource
         with respect to the namespace. The <i>nature</i> of a resource is a
         statement made about the resource itself.
      </p>
      <p>
         The <i>purpose</i> of a RDDL resource is a URI which is the
         <i>xlink:arcrole</i> of the simple XLink which describes the resource
         with respect to the namespace. The <i>purpose</i> of a resource is a
         statement made about the purpose of the resource with respect to the
         namespace.
      </p>
      <p>
         RDDL space thus identifies resources by both a <i>nature</i> and
         <i>purpose</i> much as Cartesian space identifies points by both an
         <i>x</i> and <i>y</i> coordinate.
      </p>
      </section>
	  <section><title>XML Namespaces</title>
      <p>
         If the sole reason to have namespaces is to prevent name clashes then
         the XML Namespace mechanism is not the simplest way of creating a
         namespace. This is where the controversy is created. It is widely
         acknowledged that the authors of the XML Namespaces Recommendation had
         other things in mind when <i>XML Namespaces</i> were created. Yet the
         W3C specification does not address this (perhaps because each member
         of the committee had a <i>different</i> idea of what an XML Namespace
         might be able to accomplish <font face="Wingdings">J</font> )
      </p>
      <p>
         If we look at what an XML Namespace <i>ought to be</i> rather than
         what the W3C specification actually states, then the <i>W3C XML
         Namespace</i> mechanism starts to make a lot more sense.
      </p>
      </section>
	  <section><title>Namespaces from a syntactic viewpoint</title>
      <p>
         Looking at XML Namespaces from a syntactic viewpoint: they accomplish
         the objective of partitioning XML element and attribute namespace in
         what is actually a logical and well designed fashion.
      </p>
      <p>
         This viewpoint is controversial but can be supported. The <i>XML
         Namespaces Recommendation</i> uses URIs as namespace names. Many have
         argued that a simpler hierarchical naming mechanism such as that
         selected by Sun&apos;s <i>Java</i> programming language for package
         names, would have been a simpler naming mechanism for namespace names.
         Perhaps this is true and arguably the Java package naming mechanism
         <i>could have</i> been made to work. URIs turn out to be a terrific
         and well supported way to create unique names and have some important
         advantages over Java package names when we extend the XML Namespace
         mechanism.
      </p>
	  </section>
	  <section><title>How to define namespaces as <i>spaces</i></title>
      <p>
         As a space a namespace is associated with a set of rules which define
         the space. Such rules are the &quot;Laws of Physics&quot; for the
         particular namespace.
      </p>
      <p>
         Such rules may be encoded as a set of schemas, stylesheets and
         executable code that define the properties of the namespace. The
         designer of the namespace should be free to describe the namespace
         using appropriate tools, yet we wish to have a common format with
         which to document namespaces for both human and machine use.
      </p>
	  </section>
	  <section><title>RDDL</title>
      <p>
         On December 30, 2000 in response to yet another debate on the xml-dev
         mailing list regarding whether a namespace URI ought resolve to
         anything, Tim Bray proposed that XHTML plus a bunch of XLinks would
         make a suitable format. By January 2, 2001 the RDDL acronym and basics
         of the RDDL format were formed (<a
         href="http://www.rddl.org/">http://www.rddl.org</a>) and by January 7,
         2001 the first parser was available.
      </p>
      <p>
         RDDL allows the description of many types of schemas related to a
         namespace including DTDs, XML Schema, CSS, RELAX, TREX, RDF Schema and
         Schematron.
      </p>
	  </section>
	  <section><title>RDDL DTD</title>
      <p>
         In a long tradition, the RDDL specification is itself a RDDL document
         and points to resources describing the RDDL format including a DTD:
      </p>
      <p>
         <a
         href="http://www.rddl.org/rddl-xhtml.dtd">http://www.rddl.org/rddl-xhtml.dtd</a>
      </p>
      <p>
         This snippet describes the <font
         face="Courier New">rddl:resource</font> element:
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">&lt;!ELEMENT rddl:resource
         (#PCDATA,%Flow.mix;)* &gt;</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">&lt;!ATTLIST rddl:resource</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">id ID #IMPLIED</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">	xml:lang NMTOKEN #IMPLIED</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">	xmlns:rddl CDATA
         &quot;http://www.rddl.org/&quot; #FIXED</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">	%xlink.simple.attrib;</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">	%xlink.namespace.attrib;</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">&gt;</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         The content of the <font face="Courier New">rddl:resource</font>
         element is defined similarly to the (X)HTML <font
         face="Courier New">div</font> element, and may be placed anywhere a
         <font face="Courier New">div</font> element may be in an XHTML
         document. The content is typically a human readable description of the
         resource. Providing an <font face="Courier New">id</font> attribute,
         allows a fragment identifier to index the <font
         face="Courier New">rddl:resource.</font> The xml:lang attribute is
         used to specify the language <font face="Courier New"></font>of the
         content.
      </p>
       
      <p>
         The <font face="Courier New">rddl:resource</font> element is defined
         as a simple Xlink:
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">	xl:type (simple) #FIXED
         &quot;simple&quot;</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">	xl:arcrole CDATA #IMPLIED</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">	xl:role CDATA
         &quot;http://www.rddl.org/#resource&quot;</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">	xl:href CDATA #IMPLIED</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">xl:title CDATA #IMPLIED</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">	xl:show (none) #FIXED
         &quot;none&quot;</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">	xl:embed (none) #FIXED
         &quot;none&quot;</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">	xl:label CDATA #IMPLIED</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New"> </font>
      </p>
	  </section>
	  <section><title>RDDL Nature</title>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">The RDDL <i>nature</i> or Xlink <i>role</i>
         of a resource describes the nature of the resource. This is a property
         of the resource not the namespace.</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         The <i>nature</i> is often the namespace URI of the root element of
         the related resource when the related resource is XML. When the
         related resource is not XML, the <i>nature</i> may be the well known
         URI describing its MIME <i>media type</i>.
      </p>
      <p>
         A description of some useful natures is found at <a
         href="http://www.rddl.org/natures">http://www.rddl.org/natures</a>.
         For example, the <i>nature</i> of an XML Schema document is: <a
         href="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema</a>,
         the <i>nature</i> of a Schematron schema is: <a
         href="http://www.ascc.net/xml/schematron">http://www.ascc.net/xml/schematron</a>
         and the <i>nature</i> of XSLT is <a
         href="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform">http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform</a>.
      </p>
	  </section>
	  <section><title>RDDL Purpose</title>
      <p>
         The <i>purpose</i> of a RDDL resource is defined by the namespace and
         describes the <i>purpose</i> of the resource with respect to the
         namespace. It is a property of the namespace not the resource. A list
         of some useful purposes is found at <a
         href="http://www.rddl.org/purposes/">http://www.rddl.org/purposes/</a>.
      </p>
      <p>
         The <i>purpose</i> of an XML Schema, when the schema is intended to be
         used for schema validation might be: <a
         href="http://www.rddl.org/purposes">http://www.rddl.org/purposes#schema-validation</a>.
         A namespace may use several schemas for schema validation in which
         case it can assign a more descriptive <i>purpose</i> to each schema.
      </p>
      <p>
         For example:
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">&lt;rddl:resource</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">xlink:title=&quot;TREX Schema&quot;</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font
         face="Courier New">xlink:arcrole=&quot;http://www.rddl.org/purposes#schema-validation&quot;</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font
         face="Courier New">xlink:role=&quot;http://www.thaiopensource.com/trex&quot;</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">xlink:href=&quot;xhtml-rddl.trex&quot;</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">&gt;</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">&lt;h3&gt;7.10 TREX&lt;/h3&gt;</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">&lt;p&gt;A TREX Schema &lt;a
         href=&quot;xhtml-rddl.trex&quot;&gt;xhtml-rddl.trex</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">	&lt;/a&gt; for RDDL&lt;/p&gt;</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">&lt;/rddl:resource&gt;</font>
      </p>
      </section>
	  <section>
	  <title>XML Namespaces viewed as RDDL
         Spaces</title>

      <p>
         <b>Resources and URIs</b>
      </p>
      <p>
         The <i>resource</i> is defined in RFC 2396 yet much confusion remains.
         It is commonly thought that a <i>resource</i> is a document on the web
         but this is untrue, a resource is merely a point in URI space, no more
         and no less. In common usage, however, a <i>resource</i> is
         represented by a document having a MIME media type. Via the mechanism
         known as HTTP content negotiation, for example, different documents
         may be retrieved as the representations of a single resource i.e by
         dereferencing a single URI.
      </p>
      <p>
         In practice, content negotiation is not always a useful mechanism for
         discovering properties of a particular resource. A namespace name,
         being a URI, suggests that a namespace may be considered a resource
         (or at least may be represented by a resource). By the RDDL mechanism,
         the RDDL document represents a namespace as a set of resources each
         having a <i>nature</i> and <i>purpose</i>. Thus each <i>resource</i>
         while being a point in URI Space, can be described by its own unique
         RDDL Space. At its simplest, each unique resource has a <i>set</i> of
         <i>natures.</i>
      </p>
      <p>
         <img alt="error-file:TidyOut.log" src="Image2.gif" width="301"
         height="199" />
      </p>
      <p>
         A <i>namespace</i> is defined by a set of tuples each containing an
         <i>id</i> a <i>purpose</i> and a <i>resource</i>.
      </p>
      <p>
         <img alt="error-file:TidyOut.log" src="Image3.gif" width="398"
         height="235" />
      </p>
	  </section>
	  <section>
	  <title>RDDL and RDF</title>
      <p>
         By this formalism, each RDDL resource describes two RDF triples: the
         first whose subject is the namespace URI, whose predicate is the
         <i>purpose</i> and whose object is the <i>href</i>, and the second
         whose subject is the <i>href</i> whose predicate is <i>rdf:type</i>
         and whose object is the <i>nature</i>.
      </p>
      <p>
         <img alt="error-file:TidyOut.log" src="Image4.gif" width="462"
         height="216" />
      </p>
	  </section>
	  <section><title>XSLT and RDDL</title>
      <p>
         <img alt="error-file:TidyOut.log" src="Image5.gif"
         width="574" height="268" />
      </p>
      <p>
         It is often implicit that the <i>purpose</i> of an XSLT document is to
         define a transform from one format to another. In RDDL, the namespace
         being defined may serve as the <i>nature</i> of the originating format
         and the <i>purpose</i> of the XSLT resource may be implicitly
         understood to be the <i>nature</i> of the format being transformed
         into.
      </p>
      <p>
         For example the following resource:
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">&lt;rddl:resource</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font
         face="Courier New">xl:role=&quot;http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform&quot;</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font
         face="Courier New">xl:arcrole=&quot;http://purl.org/rss/1.0&quot;</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">xl:href=&quot;toRSS.xsl&quot;</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">&gt;</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         In this case the <i>purpose</i> of the XSLT resource is to transform
         into <i>RSS</i>. The resulting document has a <i>nature</i> of <a
         href="http://purl.org/rss/1.0">http://purl.org/rss/1.0</a>. Such a
         convention allows a software agent to piece together a series of
         transforms. For example suppose it is desired to transform from format
         <i>A</i> to format <i>C</i>. The RDDL description of the namespace for
         <i>A</i> may contain an XSLT providing a transform to <i>B</i>, and
         the RDDL description for the namespace of <i>B</i> may contain an XSLT
         transform into <i>C</i>. One could then serially transform A -&gt; B
         -&gt; C.
      </p>
      </section>
	  <section><title>Software</title>

      <p>
         Software is often classified according to its nature, perhaps the
         language it is written in, and its purpose. Such a classification may
         allow a system to assemble components of a similar nature for a
         particular purpose.
      </p>
      <p>
          
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Arial">Java Resource</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         This example demonstrates the incorporation of a Java resource into a
         namespace. In this case the <i>purpose</i> of the resource is to serve
         as the implementation of an XSLT extension library associated with the
         namespace.
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">&lt;rddl:resource</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font
         face="Courier New">xl:role=&quot;...application/java-archive&quot;</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font
         face="Courier New">xl:arcrole=&quot;...purposes/software#xslt-extension&quot;</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font
         face="Courier New">xl:href=&quot;thisNS-xslt-extension.jar&quot;</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">&gt;</font>
      </p>
      <div style="margin-left: 4em">
         <p>
            <font face="Courier New">&lt;p&gt;The xslt extensions bound to this
            namespace are packaged in a JAR&lt;/p&gt;</font>
         </p>
      </div>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">&lt;/rddl:resource&gt;</font>
      </p>
      <p>
          
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Arial">RDDLURL</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         The idea of a distributed package defined by a namespace is
         implemented using a simple API. The RDDL URL implements the
         indirection through the RDDL document to obtain namespace related
         resources by nature and purpose.
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">package org.rddl;</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">class RDDLURL {</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">public RDDLURL(String nsURI,</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">			String nature,</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">			String purpose);</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">public InputStream getInputStream();</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">static Namespace getNamespace(String
         nsURI);</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">}</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New"> </font>
      </p>
       <font face="Arial"></font>
      <p>
         <font face="Arial">Interface Namespace</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         In this API a <i>namespace</i> is defined by the interface:
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">public interface Namespace {</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">	SortedMap getResourcesFromNature(String
         nature);</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">	SortedMap getResourcesFromPurpose(String
         purpose);</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">	SortedMap getResourcesFromHref(String
         href);</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">	SortedMap getResourcesFromTitle(String
         title);</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">	SortedMap getResourcesFromLang(String
         lang);</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">	SortedMap getResourcesFromIdRange(String
         id0,id1);</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">	Resource getResourceFromId(String
         id);</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">... }</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         This interface serves as a definition of an XML Namespace which is of
         practical use to software. A given <i>nature</i> or <i>purpose</i>
         defines a set of namespace related resources. Similarly the URI of a
         particular sub-resource is indicated by its <i>href</i>, yet a given
         sub-resource may be referenced by several RDDL resources (e.g.
         associated with different natures, purposes, ids etc.). As a simple
         XLink, each RDDL resource has a <i>title</i>, which serves as a short
         human readable description, and may be associated with an
         <i>xml:lang</i> attribute, which serves to distinguish the intended
         language of the documentation, or perhaps to distinguish specific
         sub-resources according to sub-resource language. Each resource may be
         given an <i>id</i> which serves as the target of a fragment
         identifier. Such <i>ids</i> allow URI references (e.g. URI +
         &quot;#&quot; + id) to target particular RDDL resources within a RDDL
         document. This is particularly useful when the id is the name of the
         resource being identified.
      </p>
      <p>
          
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Arial">Interface Resource</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">public interface Resource {</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">	String getPurpose();</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">	String getNature();</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">	String getHref();</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">	String getTitle();</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">	String getLang();</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">	String getId();</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">	String getBaseURI();</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">	Container getContainer();</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">}</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         The RDDL API definition of a <i>Resource</i> contains the expected
         RDDL attributes. Note that every <i>Resource</i> may have a specific
         <i>base URI</i>, and that every <i>Resource</i> may be associated with
         a <i>Container</i>.
      </p>
      <p>
          
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Arial">Interface Container</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">public interface Container extends Namespace
         {	</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">	Resource getResourceFromURI(String
         uri);</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">	SortedMap getResourcesFromURIRange(String
         uri0,String uri1);</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">	void addResource(Resource r);</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">}</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         A <i>Container</i> is a relatively simple extension of a
         <i>Namespace</i> with the ability to associate a <i>Resource</i> with
         an arbitrary URI, whereas all <i>Resources</i> in a particular
         <i>Namespace</i> are assumed to be based on the namespace name
         <i>URI</i>. Such resources are named by the composition of the
         namespace URI and the resource id as the fragment identifier of the
         resulting URI reference (e.g. nsURI#foo).
      </p>
      <p>
         <b><i><font face="Arial">Namespaces from a semantic
         viewpoint</font></i></b>
      </p>
      <p>
         RDDL allows XML Namespaces to be used for &quot;Semantic Web&quot;
         applications by binding URIs to particular human readable text and
         machine readable code. A simple &quot;Semantic Web&quot; code snippet
         is found in the <i>RDDLClassLoader</i> java class. This class loads
         Java classes which are bound to particular XML Namespace URIs and is
         fully described below.
      </p>
      <p>
          
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Arial">RDDLClassLoader</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">public class RDDLClassLoader extends
         java.net.URLClassLoader</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">{</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">static final String STR_NATURE_JAVA =
         &quot;http://www.rddl.org/natures#java&quot;;</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">static final String STR_NATURE_JAR =
         &quot;http://www.rddl.org/natures#JAR&quot;;</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">public RDDLClassLoader(String nsUrl,String
         purposeURI)</font>
      </p>
      <div style="margin-left: 4em">
         <p>
            <font face="Courier New">throws 	java.io.IOException,</font>
         </p>
         <div style="margin-left: 8em">
            <p>
               <font face="Courier New">org.xml.sax.SAXException{</font>
            </p>
         </div>
      </div>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">super(buildUriList(nsUrl,purposeURI));</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">}</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         It is easy to see that this class is simply the
         <i>java.net.URLClassLoader</i> class which builds its URL list via the
         set of URLs in a RDDL directory having a particular <i>purpose</i>.
         (The relevent <i>natures</i> of these resources are either
         &quot;java&quot; or &quot;JAR&quot;.)
      </p>
      <p>
         The buildURIList static member implements the functionality of the
         class:
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">protected static URL[] buildUriList(</font>
      </p>
      <div style="margin-left: 8em">
         <p>
            <font face="Courier New">java.lang.String URI,</font>
         </p>
         <p>
            <font face="Courier New">java.lang.String purposeURI)</font>
         </p>
      </div>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">{</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">		// first get the RDDL Namespace for the
         URI</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">	Namespace ns =
         RDDLURL.getNamespace(URI);</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">		SortedMap ress0 =
         ns.getResourcesFromNature( STR_NATURE_JAVA );</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">	TreeMap ress = new TreeMap(ress0);</font>
      </p>
      <div style="margin-left: 4em">
         <div style="margin-left: 4em">
            <p>
               <font face="Courier New">// merge STR_NATURE_JAVA and
               STR_NATURE_JAR
               ress.putAll(ns.getResourcesFromNature(STR_NATURE_JAR));</font>
            </p>
            <p>
               <font face="Courier New">// create a Vector of values having the
               desired</font>
            </p>
            <p>
               <font face="Courier New">// purpose</font>
            </p>
            <p>
               <font face="Courier New">Vector strArr = new Vector();</font>
            </p>
         </div>
         <p>
            <font face="Courier New">Iterator iter =
            ress.values().iterator();</font>
         </p>
         <p>
            <font face="Courier New">while(iter.hasNext())</font>
         </p>
         <p>
            <font face="Courier New">{</font>
         </p>
      </div>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">Resource res = (Resource)iter.next();</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">if
         (purposeURI.equals(res.getPurpose()))</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">strArr.addElement(res.getHref());</font>
      </p>
      <div style="margin-left: 4em">
         <p>
            <font face="Courier New">}</font>
         </p>
         <p>
            <font face="Courier New">// convert to URL[]</font>
         </p>
         <p>
            <font face="Courier New">int len = strArr.size();</font>
         </p>
         <p>
            <font face="Courier New">URL[] uris = new URL[len];</font>
         </p>
         <p>
            <font face="Courier New">URL baseURL = new URL(URI);</font>
         </p>
         <p>
            <font face="Courier New">for(int i=0;i&lt;len;i++){</font>
         </p>
      </div>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">uris[i] = new URL(</font>
      </p>
      <div style="margin-left: 8em">
         <p>
            <font face="Courier New">baseURL,</font>
         </p>
         <p>
            <font face="Courier New">(String)strArr.elementAt(i));</font>
         </p>
      </div>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">		};</font>
      </p>
      <div style="margin-left: 4em">
         <p>
            <font face="Courier New">return uris;</font>
         </p>
      </div>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">}</font>
      </p>
      <br />
      <br />
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">}</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New"> </font>
      </p>
       <font face="Arial"></font>
      <p>
         <font face="Arial">Efficiency Concerns</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         Concerns raised with RDDL/Namespace applications generally fall into
         two issues:
      </p>
      <ol>
         <li>
            Resolution of well known namespace URIs will create a bottleneck.
         </li>
         <li>
            RDDL places an extra level of URI resolution indirection that
            imposes inefficiency.
         </li>
      </ol>
      <p>
         Frequent resolving of namespace URIs such as XML Schema would create a
         bottleneck just as would frequent downloading of HTML DTDs. Thankfully
         the Web has evolved mechanisms to deal with such issues including
         caches and local catalog indirection. Many applications will hardwire
         schemas such as for HTML and work around such bottlenecks.
      </p>
      <p>
         Regarding the RDDL indirection, how and when an application binds to a
         resource is an implementation issue and need not impose significant
         actual overhead. Approaches toward dealing with these issues include
         <i>namespace precompilation</i>.
      </p>
      <p>
          
      </p>
      <p>
         <b><font face="Arial">RDDL HTTP Extension Framework</font></b>
      </p>
      <p>
         There is no particular need for a RDDL document to be downloaded to
         the client. RDDL defines a set of HTTP Extension Framework headers
         which allow server side indirection:
      </p>
      <p>
         For example the following HTTP Request can be used to request the
         appropriate XML Schema used to validate the namespace:
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">GET / HTTP/1.1 Host: www.rddl.org Opt:
         &quot;http://www.rddl.org/httpext&quot;; ns=11</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">11-Nature:
         http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema</font>
      </p>
      <p>
         <font face="Courier New">11-Purpose:</font> <a
         href="http://www.rddl.org/purposes"><font
         face="Courier New">http://www.rddl.org/purposes#schema-validation</font></a>
      </p>
      </section>
      <p>
         <b><i><font face="Arial">Putting it all together</font></i></b>
      </p>
      <p>
         Mixing together terms from different namespaces in a single document
         or collection of documents raises particular challenges which we are
         just starting to understand.
      </p>
      <p>
         Biomedical information serves as an example of the intermingling of
         namespace specific vocabularies. Many groups and organizations have
         developed specialized lexicons which might be documented at individual
         namespaces. For example &quot;BioML&quot; for genetics/bioinformatics,
         &quot;CPT&quot; codes for surgery/procedures, &quot;SNOMED&quot; for
         pathology, &quot;ICD&quot; for medicine and &quot;DICOM&quot; for
         radiology.
      </p>
      <p>
         An &quot;electronic medical record&quot; might be expected to contain
         documents coded in each of these lexicons.
      </p>
      <p>
          
      </p>
      <p>
         <img alt="error-file:TidyOut.log" src="Image6.gif" width="384"
         height="233" />
      </p>
      <p>
         In order to make sense of such apparently disparate information a set
         of term equivalencies might be created via a set of hyperlinks.
      </p>
      <p>
         <img alt="error-file:TidyOut.log" src="Image7.gif" width="493"
         height="269" />
      </p>
      <p>
         Much as we might view a namespace as defining the <i>shape of
         information</i>, the activity of analyzing documents which contain
         linkages between terms in multiple namespaces may be helped by
         considering the <i>shape of ontologies</i>
      </p>
      <p>
         <img alt="error-file:TidyOut.log" src="Image8.gif" width="484"
         height="203" />
      </p>
</body>
</paper>

